So, I was thinking about what to teach
this morning.
We'll be going through the Lamrim.
We've been doing it about
13 or 14 years.
So,
my teacher
taught me
the steps to the path
for three times through the book, which
took 30 years.
And
so, I was trying to do it once with you
guys.
And we're about
We're doing really well. I think we have
a maybe a few months to go.
And
The theory before I started this Lamrim
was that all the Lamrims end
in the last two perfections, meditation
and emptiness.
And
when I taught this Lamrim, I decided to
do the meditation and emptiness first.
So, we went to the end of the book when
we started.
And I taught meditation and emptiness,
and then we started from the beginning
of the book.
And we're almost reached the part that
we started with. And
so, we're finishing finishing the book.
But I promised to do one more
meditation and and emptiness section
from another Lamrim.
And I was thinking the
Lamrim Chenmo of Tsongkhapa, which is
the great Lamrim. And uh
He's is a thousand pages. He spends 500
pages on emptiness.
And
and meditation, which is why Pabongka
Rinpoche did not
spend many pages on it cuz he said,
"What's the use, you know?"
Uh
And then
I've been working on the Mixed Nuts
books.
We just finished the 11th one last
night.
Uh and uh
There's a book I was started about, mhm,
9 years ago,
called Gom Bor Rap So, which is, uh,
the
true intent or something like that of
the Buddha.
And it's on Tsongkhapa's, uh,
greatest work on emptiness.
It will be about, uh, 1,500 pages in
English, I think.
Uh,
and, uh, so I I started it and I never
had time to finish it.
Uh,
cuz I'm too busy.
I'm about halfway through, so I thought,
um,
I would pause,
uh, working on the Mixed Nuts books.
I'll still do the translation classes,
but I thought I would pause it for about
6 months. Uh, usually I work all day on
their books,
and I would like to finish the
Gom Bor Rap So, which is the
greatest book ever written on emptiness.
And then I thought it would be fun to
teach that instead of the Lam Rim Tsema
emptiness, cuz, uh,
it's actually deeper. It's much deeper
about emptiness, and, uh,
no one's really translated it yet, and I
don't think anybody will
or can, so, um, anyway, I'm thinking
about that. Uh,
so last night, pretty much last night I
finished this book. This is Sage's book.
And, uh,
we finished it. Uh, kind of I'm doing
the table of contents last night.
And, um, it's a famous book on Lojong.
Uh, Lojong means, well, we'll talk about
it.
But it's basically compassion teachings,
how to develop a good heart. And, um,
this is a tea teaching on a lojong that
was taught a thousand years ago.
It was basically the first teaching that
came from Tibet to
uh sorry, from India to Tibet.
And uh a thousand years ago. And it was
called the Sanjay Kalo, which means the
crown of knives.
Uh the the crown that cuts your head
open.
And uh that was a famous uh lojong text
about a thousand years ago.
Uh
so I thought um
I'm kind of in the mood for this
cuz uh I just spent about 4 months
working on it.
And um
it's amazing. It's a commentary that was
given about uh
two 200 years ago. And uh
And it's amazing. And so
uh
I thought I would tell you a little bit
about this book. And then I'll leave it
up here and you guys can look at it. Uh
I don't
our publishing
team is a little behind.
Like 3 years.
Uh
so I don't know how soon it's going to
get out. Hopefully soon.
But uh it's a beautiful book. And
so there's a
uh I I wrote an introduction. It's about
100 pages and it's good.
And it's the history of lojong. And uh
this lojong lojong means
so I'll tell you what it means cuz we're
in the middle of it
in
So we just start going through the
lojong
uh part in Pabongka's Lamrim. After 14
years or 13 years, we've reached the
lojong part.
Uh
so here's what lojong means. Um
thousand years ago
uh there was an Indian
uh master called Atisha.
He His other name is Dipankara. Uh
sometimes they call him Jowo Je, which
means the Lord.
And uh
he lived in India a thousand years ago.
He was attending a
monastery named Vikramashila.
And uh Vikrama means damn good.
Shila means morality. Probably they
wouldn't say that if they had good
morality, but uh
it's the name of the monastery. That and
Nalanda are the two great Buddhist
monasteries in ancient India.
So, he was a a master there and he
people would go to
uh
Vajrasana.
Uh Vajra means diamond, asana means
seat.
Like under your ass.
That's really where the word comes from.
Uh
so anyway, Vajrasana means uh seat of
the diamond. And it's the old name for
Bodh Gaya,
uh which is where Lord Buddha was
enlightened.
And uh
in fact, the first time we finished the
Diamond Cutter Sutra
translation into English,
the first time I ever taught it was uh
sitting under the Bodhi tree.
And uh Bodh Gaya, and it was awesome.
Uh
that was 100 years ago, right?
And uh anyway,
so people used to go there and walk
around the stupa
uh for good luck. And so, Atisha went
there.
100 bucks if you can tell me the Tibetan
for Atisha.
Yeah, Punzo. So, Haggerty pay Haggerty
$100.
Left hand to right hand.
Yeah, he's he's got it ready.
Yeah, Prince Atisha means the perfect
perfect
perfectly good person, perfect Atisha.
Uh
so, anyway, uh he was walking around the
stupa of Bodhgaya.
And they say he looked up in the sky and
there were two ladies talking.
And one was younger, one was older. And
and one lady
I don't know, he he doesn't seem like he
was too worried that they were sitting
in the sky.
He's like, "Oh, you know." And
the one lady said to the other lady, you
know, "If you wanted to get
enlightened uh really fast,
you know, what would be the best way?"
And the other lady said, "Sem Jong. Sem
Jong."
Say Sem Jong.
Okay, you got to say twice. Sem Jong.
Yeah.
And then that's all. Then they like
disappeared and you know, Atisha's like,
"Sem Jong. Sem Jong."
Sem means
mind. Jong means to practice something
until you're good at it, okay?
It also means to purify something or to
clean something.
So, Sem Jong means that and they
repeated it twice.
And then he said, "Well,
I got to find out how to Sem Jong, you
know." So, he
asked around, "Who knows about Sem
Jong?"
And somebody said, "Oh, there's a great
master
uh
named Dharmakirti."
So, Dharmakirti already dead for 300
years, you know. And Atisha said, "Well,
he's been passed away."
I'll slow down translate. I can already
see you're stressed.
Uh
Dharmakirti lived about 350
years before Atisha.
And he's the great logician.
And you don't want to meet him.
Uh, cuz it's very difficult. In fact, I
moved one of the translation classes out
of this week.
Uh, so you wouldn't have a breakdown.
And uh
So, we're going to do Vinaya instead.
Uh, morality, okay? But anyway, so
they said, "No, no, that's not not that
Dharmakirti. There's two Dharmakirtis."
And he said, "Well, who's the second
Dharmakirti?"
And they said, "Oh, he's uh living in
in Indonesia. You know, he's a great
master in Indonesia."
Uh, and this is called Sumatra, right?
Uh, an island in Indonesia. I think
there's over a thousand islands in
Indonesia. One is called Sumatra.
To get to Sumatra in the old days, a
thousand years ago,
uh, Chinese
masters used to leave
uh, from what's now Guangzhou.
Uh, they used to leave from the port
there in Guangzhou. And then they would
sail to uh Sumatra
and uh study there. And uh there was a a
thousand monks there
at a place called Palembang or
something. And they
So, if you wanted to go to India to
study,
uh, because people were inspired by monk
called Xuanzang.
Uh, 400 years before that, he went to
India.
He walked to India across the Gobi
Desert and then
down through Afghanistan, walked through
India,
17 years.
And he learned Buddhism. And then he
became a great debater. He beat
a huge bunch of Indian monks at Nalanda
Monastery.
Then he came home with all with a
thousand Buddhist books to Xi'an, which
was then called
Chang'an, and there was a tower there
that the Tang Taizong, the emperor
Tang Chao, Tang Dynasty gave him a
tower. I get stuck with this two-story
building.
Xuanzang had a tower like 20 high 15
stories. I went there.
Uh but anyway,
uh
so he he basically helped start
uh Chinese Buddhism as we know it now
uh with a thousand different
translations from his team.
And then about 350 years later,
uh
you know, monks were going from China to
Indonesia
and studying there, and then they would
learn Sanskrit roughly,
and then they would take the sea journey
around
Indonesia, Vietnam,
uh all the way to Burma
to uh Bengal, and then they would walk
to Nalanda monastery.
And that's where the real study was
going on.
But they had to kind of prepare in
Indonesia first.
So anyway, there were some great monks
teaching in Indonesia. One of them was
named Dharmakirti.
Uh sometimes Indonesia or Sumatra was
called
the island of the gold, Suvarna
dvipa. Say Suvarna.
Dvipa.
Uh Suvarna means good color.
Uh varna came into English varnish,
which means the paint on a on a table or
something. Suvarna means uh good color,
golden.
And dvipa, ba means water,
and dvipa means split the water,
which is what an
island does.
So, Dvipa means island. So, Suvana Dvipa
is the lama from the golden island.
And people told Atisha, "If you want to
learn Semjong,
if you want to learn
the mind, to purify the mind, study the
mind, you got to go to Indonesia." So,
he took off on a boat
13 months uh at sea.
And he had I found out later he had 125
students with him. But like to take two
students is a pain in the butt.
And I don't know how he survived with
125 and when Atisha
later went to Tibet, he only took one or
two students with him. Probably he
learned
uh
But uh anyway, there's a beautiful
story.
And he's
he got to uh into Sumatra
and he met Suvana Dvipa guru, the the
teacher from the golden island.
And he said, "Will you teach me
Semjong?
Will you teach me By the way, which
means bodhicitta.
Uh which we can say compassion, okay?
And uh
And the teacher said, "Yeah, I can teach
you, but it takes a while. Okay, are you
ready to commit?"
And he said, "Well, how long is a
while?" And he said, "About 12 years."
You know? And Atisha said, "That's fine.
I'll I'll I'll do it."
And he stayed in Indonesia for 12 years.
And he studied uh Semjong, okay?
Uh And then when he got back to
India,
uh he met he had three great teacher He
had 157
gurus.
Three greatest ones. And uh one of the
other ones was named Maitri Yogi, okay?
Uh my Say Maitri.
Yogi.
Uh
he was a great master of Lojong.
So, all three were great masters of
Lojong. And uh Maitri Yogi's famous
story is that
he uh
uh he was giving a public lecture
in a town square in India.
I think he was standing on a soap box.
This is a American thing. You stand on a
wooden box to talk to a group of people
in the old days.
And uh somebody in the back was hassling
with a dog. If you've ever lived in
India, there's dogs
wild dogs running around everywhere. And
the dog sniffed at the man, and the man
took a stick and
whacked him three times. And then uh
Maitri Yogi, Atisha's second teacher,
he goes
Like he could feel the stick, you know?
And then the guy's the the guy's like,
"Ah, come on, you know, you
you're just pretending you can feel the
dog's pain, you know?" And Maitri Yogi
says, "Oh, yeah?" And he turns around
and he lifts up his robes,
and you can see his bottom.
And there's three red
welts across his butt, you know? And he
says, "See?"
The guy's like, "Okay, I believe you."
So, um
that's his story. He taught Lojong to
Atisha, two two people.
Uh then he had a third teacher in India
named Dharma
Rakshita. Say Dharma.
Rakshita.
And uh he was a great master of Lojong
also. And uh he
he was
he saw that
uh
he started teaching Atisha Abhidharma,
okay?
And there at the time there was a
the great exposition of Abhidharma. So,
Abhidharma was popular
after Buddha for
about 700 years. Uh the Abhidharma guys
took over
Buddhism.
And they were amazingly dull
and boring, okay? And uh I know I
studied Abhidharma with my That's the
first thing I studied with my teacher.
Usually in the Geshe course you study it
last.
But but my teacher was teaching it to
somebody, so I
I did 12 years of Abhidharma with my
teacher and it's it's very dull
and very boring. So, anyway, they kind
of took over Buddhism for
700 years, these guys. And so, they had
these huge books,
like thousands of pages. And
Dharmarakshita
was teaching it to Atisha. So, Atisha
was getting fed
Abhidharma. And Abhidharma teaching on
emptiness is very strange
and uh
not very sophisticated. And it it
doesn't help you a lot.
It's extremely similar to modern
science. So, the Abhidharma
system
of understanding reality and modern
science are almost exactly the same.
Uh so, that was 2,000 years ago. And
so, he was getting fed this long slow
book
of Abhidharma. And uh
his teacher Dharmarakshita was went to
town.
And there was um
a guy uh dying. There was a man dying in
his home.
And uh there was a doctor
uh taking care of him.
And the doctor,
you know,
announced that the only way this guy is
going to survive
is if somebody
cuts a piece of human flesh
off their body and feed it to him.
Otherwise, he'll die, you know. So,
Dharmarakshita is like, "Okay,
I can do that." And he took a knife and
he
cut a big piece of steak off his leg,
off his thigh here. It made a terrible
wound.
And they fed the meat to the
to the guy and he got better
almost right away, you know. And uh
everybody was amazed and and then
Dharmarakshita had to go to bed cuz he
couldn't stand anymore.
And he he went into a dream
uh
and uh Maitreya came to him uh
and said uh "Hey, something happened to
your leg." And you know,
and Dharmarakshita is like, "Oh, yeah, I
had to offer some of my meat
to somebody." And Maitreya puts his hand
on on his thigh
and cured him
in the dream.
Uh
and then Dharmarakshita woke up
and he he looked and his leg was all
fixed, you know. And then suddenly he
said, "Why am I wasting time on
Abhidharma? I can't do emptiness that
way."
And because of the blessing of Maitreya,
he he actually became a mind only.
He started to follow the mind only
school.
Which is like
really good. It's not the ultimate, but
it's really good.
And uh so,
Dharmarakshita studied uh mind only. He
became a mind only master.
And he taught that to Atisha.
And uh and like that. And he said it was
the blessing of Maitreya that caused him
to
to change his school Uh to to that.
So,
that was the background of Atisha.
Later, Atisha got teachings on
Nagarjuna.
And the six books of Nagarjuna,
sometimes they say five books, and he
became a great master of emptiness also.
Then there was um
kings in Tibet. They wanted to bring
Buddhism to Tibet.
There had been some Buddhism came to
Tibet with individual yogis
like few hundred years before.
So, Buddhism came to China like 700
years before Tibet.
Uh
but in in Tibet, it was around the time
of Atisha that the the main teachers the
main teachings reached Tibet.
And Atisha was planning to go to
He was asked to come to Tibet
and teach uh by the king.
And the king was trying to
fundraise, as I can appreciate,
uh
to get Atisha to
Tibet.
And then he was fundraising in a
neighboring kingdom.
And that king imprisoned him
and said he would kill him unless his
people gave him gold.
And there was a big fight and uh
the king actually died in prison. And
then his nephew
uh
decided to try to invite Atisha to
Tibet.
And they sent
It's a long long story, but they sent a
team to
India
to try to convince the abbot of
Vikramashila to release Atisha.
And
eventually they made a deal that Atisha
would stay for 3 years
in Tibet.
And, uh, he would teach for 3 years.
Atisha was already 57 years old.
Uh,
in in those days, the average age was
40, 45. You know, you survived to 40 or
45. He was already
like 12 years over
maximum age. And, nowadays, he'd be 90
or something.
And, uh, so, it was difficult for him to
travel, but he agreed to go.
And, uh, he went to Tibet. And, uh,
they met a
they met a strange man on the way.
Single man traveling.
And, they said, uh,
he said, "Oh, you guys look like you're
going somewhere important, you know. You
look like you're on a mission."
You know, and they said, "Yeah, we're
trying to bring Buddhism to a new
country. This country doesn't even have
an alphabet.
Okay? This is a country of yak herders
and warriors.
You know, they don't they don't have
books. They don't have writing.
You know, and we're going to He says,
"Well, that's going to be hard. I'll
teach you some prayers."
And, they He taught them some prayers to
to say,
uh, about compassion.
And, there's a,
tradition that that was
Dromtön Gyalwe Jungne. So, Dromtön
Gyalwe
was the first Tibetan to receive
teachings from Atisha.
And,
by the way, I put all these stories in
the introduction, okay?
It took me a long time.
Uh, and I had to read a lot of ancient
books, then it was fun.
But, uh, Dromtön Gyalwe,
uh, he was born in Tibet,
central Tibet,
uh around 1,000 AD and uh
it's interesting cuz normally in the
stories of the great teachers,
they don't tell you any information.
They just tell you he was the most
wonderful and the greatest and you know,
and they go on like that for 100 pages
and then there's no information.
And there's a few uh
historians who will tell you the truth,
you know.
So, I found one
and he said uh Domton Jay
was born his parents were Bonpo. Bonpo
means uh
shamans. They were both shamans. They
were not Buddhist.
So, at that time in Tibet,
uh most people were shaman and they
worshipped the sky Tengri.
And it's a long story, Bonpo, and uh so
we know from their personal names
that they weren't Buddhist. They were
shaman.
And uh they had this boy and then I
don't know after
like
when he was 13, his father took a second
wife,
which was common in Tibet at that time
or or two brothers would share the same
wife. Uh and so he
he didn't get along with his stepmother,
which is very rare.
And uh
and he moved out, which is also very
rare.
And uh he went he went off and he met
some
lama, you know, and the lama he asked
the lama to teach him.
And cuz he heard the lama was going to
go to India
and study there, so he thought I'll
attach myself to this lama
and maybe he'll take me to India with
him, you know. So, he did.
And the lama said, "Look, you're too
young for me to travel
take you traveling cuz people will say I
stole you from your parents or
something.
I guess 15 was the
driving age or something.
You know, he said wait another year or
two and you can travel with me.
And then he went to Nepal. He tried to
he met some Indian masters. He He did a
What do you call it? Clairvoyance
contest? Who can read the other person's
mind?
And uh the Tibetan llama won.
And then he said, "Ah, why waste my time
in India? I think I'll go back to
Tibet."
And he went back to Tibet and he
he took Dromtonpa.
Uh
Drom, by the way, Drom
Drom is a place in Tibet. Ton means
teacher from
wherever. So, when you say ton at the
end of a person's name,
it means tonpa, which means teacher.
So, you know, you could call Arizona
Arizona Arizona Arizona ton
would be the teacher from Arizona or
something like that. So, he's Dromton.
His monk's name is Gyalway Jungnay,
which means the source of victorious
Buddhas. Okay? And so, anyway,
the
teacher told him, "Look,
I have to go to East Tibet, which is
called Kham,
and you can travel with me. It's a
thousand miles
you know, on horseback and and you can
come with me, but you have to do
whatever I say
or else I don't need the trouble." Which
I also appreciate.
And
so,
he's like Dromtonpa is like, "I promise
whatever you need I'll do, you know."
And so, he got
stuck with watching the
the horses all night. What do you call a
horse guard?
And in Tibet at the time that involved
uh
picking thorn bushes like cactuses with
your hands
and setting them around the cattle so
they couldn't get out and people
couldn't get in. So he had to be pulling
cactuses up with his bare hands
uh
you know, all evening and then guarding
the
and then during the day uh his teacher
made him
crush barley
powder
cuz of tsampa they need to eat it in
their breakfast, right?
And my lama did the same thing to me
and I know I know what it's like and you
you take a
this thing called a thing
it's a
heavy heavy piece of metal pipe this
thing with a bottom and then they give
you a heavy heavy uh
metal rod
and you you drop a few barley corns in
there and you smash them and then you
take them out and you smash more and it
takes like four or five hours and my
teacher insisted it
it was the only way that tsampa would
taste good
if you did it by hand. So I I went
through that. I did many many many hours
crushing barley, you know. I said,
"Let's use a machine." He's like, "No,
it puts oil in the barley.
It ruins the taste, you know." So
apparently Dromtonpa's teacher said the
same thing.
And uh so he was crushing barley during
the day, he was watching horses at
night, he didn't get any study. He was
frustrated.
Uh
but then, you know, people asked him
later, "Did you feel
upset at the lama?" And he said, "Well,
actually no.
I thought it was an honor to serve my
teacher, you know." And uh so he didn't
he didn't complain. Finally some of uh
his teachers, friends,
said, "Why are you wasting his time?
You know, he could be a great Geshe. He
could He could be studying, you know.
Why are you wasting his time
uh guarding horses and, you know,
smashing barley?"
So, they were passing a lot of
monasteries and uh
he he had been teaching him.
And he said, "Okay,
uh sometimes you can go in the
monasteries and debate with the monks."
And this way, Dromton Gyalwa became a
great debater.
In the meantime, uh Atisha is trying to
get over the mountains in Nepal into
Tibet.
And Tara comes to him. By the way, the
two ladies were Tara and Vajrayogini
in the sky. And uh Tara comes to him and
says,
"Uh keep an eye Keep your eye out for
the Upasika. Upasika means uh
a uh lay layman layperson with lifetime
vows. So, uh Dromton Gyalwa is famous.
He was the first great Tibetan Buddhist.
Uh but he never became a monk. Uh he was
a layman.
And uh he never went higher than taking
his uh five vows or eight vows. So, he
kept those vows his whole life.
And And he
So, in Sanskrit, it's called Upasaka or
Upasika.
And Tara told Atisha,
"Keep your eyes out for the Upasika
cuz he's going to help you in Tibet, you
know." And so,
So, uh
Atisha entered Tibet through Nepal,
which is West Tibet,
and in a province called Ngari.
And it's the far western side of Tibet.
Uh Dromton Gyalwa was smashing barley
and picking thorns in the east
a thousand miles away.
And then in one day and he was learning
to debate and then one day he uh
he decided he would like to learn
Sanskrit
because if he ever met an Indian teacher
he could talk to him.
Uh so he
he found a
a teacher called the Dharma which means
uh
thorn
of Sanskrit. It means he was a tough
teacher.
Like nail.
You know. And he taught him Sanskrit.
And then Drumton Jay asked his Sanskrit
teacher
are there still any great
teachers left in India?
And he says, "Well, there's Naropa
who could teach you Vajrayogini
but he's getting really old. He may have
passed away already. And then Shantipa
who's similar.
And then there's a new young guy named
Atisha.
You know, and he's pretty good. And and
when Drumton Jay heard the name
Atisha his heart starts
going crazy and he's like, "Oh, that's
my teacher, you know.
I got to meet him, you know." And then
he heard
that Atisha had had climbed over Nepal
and entered Nari, west Tibet. And he and
he asked his teacher
and he was afraid because the teacher
thought if the teacher might be jealous.
We we have a word for that in Tibet. Um
like professional jealousy. Like
there's a word for that. And um so he
said
"Would you mind if I
I've served you for 13 years. Could I
just go meet this other teacher cuz my
heart beats fast whenever I think about
him and
and he says, "Yeah, go for it, you
know." And here's a horse.
And he says, "Well, the horse is all
loaded
with boxes." He says, "Yeah, I got it
ready for you."
"What's in the boxes?" "Scriptures."
"Have a nice time."
You know, read them on your way, you
know. And so, he took off
uh
to uh West of Bedrock and jumped in
there riding as fast as he could.
And there's a beautiful story that he
stopped in a place called uh he stopped
in a
in an empty place, kind of like Diamond
Mountain, and uh
there was a manor house, like a large
house. Fancy
mud house, right?
And there was a lot of partying going on
inside the house and uh
he uh he's thirsty and he's tired and he
needs a place to sleep and maybe some
food or something. And he says, "Who
what's going on, you know?" And they
say, "Well,
that's a guy named Cabell. Cabell is uh
Cabell Jr. and Cabell Sr.
are the two owners of this area. They're
the big ranchers. They're like, "What's
those ranchers' name next door?"
Huh? The Clumps. They're like the
Clumps, okay?
May you never meet the Clumps.
I met them once. They had all these
guns, you know. I'm like,
"What's the guns for?" And they said,
"We shoot rattlesnakes." I'm like,
"Okay, just rattlesnakes, right?"
And anyway, they're like the Clumps of
that area and they're like By the way,
they own the
the marble quarry, so we're we're
actually getting along with them.
And uh
so anyway, he said, "They're the big
shots around here." He says, "I'm really
thirsty. I'll take a chance. He walks
into the house. Younger cupboard is
there.
You know, spoiled rich kid.
And he's like
Where are you from? East Tibet. They
talk funny.
People from East Tibet, they talk really
funny.
So everybody else knows where they're
from.
And they're like, you talk funny. You
must be from East Tibet. He's like,
yeah.
He says, okay. He says, well, if you
want to
If you want something to drink or eat,
you're going to have to prostrate to me,
says the younger
cupboard, the rich spoiled rich kid.
And
and Domton Jay says, I don't have a
problem with that.
What kind of prostration do you want,
you know? And the kid said, I want the
vomiting fox prostration.
You know,
and
you go down like this and then you
stretch a long way and then you put your
head down and then you come back and
then
It's like a fox vomiting. That.
And
I I found one on YouTube.
And it's just like that.
Somebody took a video. I don't know how.
You can look it up.
But they go
He did the fox vomiting prostration to
cupboard junior.
And then they sat down and they start
having refreshments and
Then they after a while cupboard says
You wouldn't be that
Domton Jay, would you? From East Tibet.
He's famous already for
debating the monks in the monastery and
beating them.
And and Domton Jay's like, yeah, that's
me. And he goes, oh, I'm so sorry.
I didn't know it was Domton Jay, you
And he takes his seat like and he gives
it to Dromtonpa and he I'm so sorry
about the prostration thing. And
Dromtonpa is like, "Don't worry about
it."
Like he's very chill guy.
And he's like, "Don't worry about it.
It's okay." And they start talking and
Kadampa says
"By the way, I'm really rich and I'm
going to build
uh
another large house here as a temple.
And I need a temple keeper.
And would you be interested, you know?"
And Dromtonpa is like, "First of all,
by the way, Dromtonpa has
got this mission. He can see
what Atisha's going to do in Tibet.
He can see what's going to happen.
And he's already thinking of how to
fundraise, right?
And he's like, "Well,
you know,
if it was a big temple, I might be
interested.
You know? And and the guy says, "Well,
I'll make it pretty big." He says, "No,
I mean like a castle."
And Kadampa is like, "Okay, I could do a
castle."
And he says, "Okay, you build a castle
and on my way back,
I'll stop and I'll see if it's big
enough, I'll stay."
You know? And on the way
back,
17 years later,
uh
he's got this big castle and that was
Rabten Monastery.
That became Rabten Monastery. That
became Dromtonpa's. That became the
first great Tibetan Monastery.
And uh Atisha and Dromtonpa taught
there. And that's where the Lamrim was
first taught.
And that's where Lojong was first
taught. And that's where Tsongkhapa had
the vision to write the Lamrim Chenmo.
And if you know the source of all my
good,
uh
that's where he spoke those words.
So, uh Roding is a very important place.
And they built it just for Atisha to
teach, you see?
Anyway,
then he set out from Dromton Gyalwe
heads
off to the
west. He's still
Kawa gives him a new fresh horse, like a
a really beautiful horse and as a gift
and he's
galloping and he runs into a war.
And there were lots of local wars going
on.
There's a joke in Tibetan.
There's a Machik Labdrön Gyalmo.
There's somebody's having a major
war.
I think three people died.
Anyway, uh so he couldn't get
to west Tibet on the road. It's called
the north road and Changlam.
And he had to go through the forest and
he got lost in the forest.
And then uh
he found a deer. He ran into a deer, you
know? And I was doing retreat in
Flagstaff uh
many years ago, like 25 years ago and uh
a deer
uh I met a deer in the forest.
And we just like ran into each other and
and
and I was and I I thought, I'll sing the
mandala offering to him and and see what
happens. And he did he stayed there.
And he was like, wow, you know?
And um
so he met this deer and the deer the
deer is like
you know?
So, he followed the deer a long long way
and he found the house where Atisha was
staying.
And
they say that some people say the deer
was Tara.
Uh and then other people say was Pehar.
Pehar is a uh protector, Danny.
Not the protector Danny, okay?
Uh
who helped uh Padmasambhava
uh two or 300 years before that. Uh
and they they founded the monastery
called Samye,
which is very important for Atisha and
Dromton Gyalpo. So, anyway,
this deer took him to
Atisha's house and uh
and he went in the house and he said,
you know, he's all dirty and crazy and
sweaty and he says, "Where's Atisha?"
And they say,
"He's been waiting for you.
Tara told him you're on the way.
And you were supposed to be here this
afternoon.
Tara said you would be here this
afternoon, you know. And then uh
you didn't show up, so Atisha went to do
prayers at somebody's house, you know.
And uh just relax and have something to
drink and
you know,
he'll come back. He's just doing prayers
at somebody's house.
And uh Dromton Gyalpo's like, "Are you
crazy? You know, if what if I die in the
next 10 minutes, you know?
I'm going to go find him, you know." And
he like runs out of the house and he's
running down the street and he uh
he runs into Atisha cuz Atisha's by like
57, you know, he's old.
And he can't walk very fast and he
he starts uh prostrating to him crazy.
And Atisha
blesses him and and then they go to the
house of the sponsor.
And uh
this and and Atisha says, "This is the
guy that was supposed to be here
earlier.
Uh
and I told you to make an extra meal for
him." And the the sponsor said, "Yeah.
Yeah, I remember. I got it already, you
know. I got a big hunk of
Tibetan bread and a big
butter ball of butter, you know."
So, Atisha gives the bread and butter to
Dromton Gyalpo.
And then they do the prayers, and then
the Dromton Gyalpo decides to eat the
bread and save the butter cuz he has an
idea. And he goes back
They go back to the house.
And uh Atisha has been keeping a
a tempting vase near the his pillow
for 3 days cuz Tara said the guy will be
here in 3 days.
The Upasaka, right? And uh
So,
you know, Atisha gives him tantric
initiation immediately.
And then Dromton Gyalpo uh
burns the butter. What do you call
Clarifies the butter, makes it ghee.
And offers to
a butter lamp to his teacher. And he did
that every night for the rest of his
life. Uh he offered a
butter lamp at the pillow of his
teacher.
And then they started and and Dromton
Gyalpo's like,
"So, you're going to teach the Tibetans
Buddhism, right? And and
Atisha's like, "Yeah."
And Dromton Gyalpo's like, "Well,
they don't know anything.
And they're really rough people.
And uh
you know,
it's not going to be easy. Do you have
something
kind of easy for them?"
And Atisha says, "Yeah, the two angels
told me
Who?
Ah.
The two angels said Sem Jong, Sem Jong.
I got Sem Jong for you guys. Uh let's
call it Lojong.
Okay, Lo and Sem are the same thing. So,
he said, "Let's call it lojong. I
brought you a lojong."
And
so, lojong is like first
introductory
Buddhism.
And if you're going to teach a whole
country of crazy people
like Americans,
then you might want to start with
lojong.
And my teacher used to start with
And the first thing he taught me was
lojong.
And there's a famous lojong in eight
verses.
He taught it to me. That was the first
teaching he ever gave me.
Uh they asked me here on next Saturday.
Is it Saturday?
We're going to have a 20th anniversary
or of what?
Diamond.
And uh
they said, "Will you teach something?"
And I said, "Let's do the lojong."
The eight verses, okay? Lojong Sikyong,
which is uh the teacher is called
Dorje Sempa, which means diamond lion.
And it's a very, very profound uh
lojong because it covers both semjongs.
Okay, semjong semjong.
And it covers both aspects of lojong.
So,
uh
By the way, so Atisha started
with lojong. And he didn't do the eight
verses. He did the crown of knives,
which is what this is, okay? This is the
crown of knives.
Uh the actual lojong is 100 verses,
roughly.
The commentary is, you know,
800 pages, okay?
And uh
So,
uh he taught that one. His teacher,
Shunt uh Dharmarakshita,
gave him that lojong. He taught him that
lojong.
Uh
which is at the time it's called Asidara
Chakra. So, asi means uh
asi means uh steel sword.
Dara means uh holding a steel sword.
And uh chakra means a crown
uh or a wheel. So, Asidara Chakra is the
ancient name for
a weapon.
And Stanley found me the Chinese
version, which is called blood dripper.
It's like a ninja
thing. What do you call it?
Say it again.
Shak Dee?
Shak Dee Sa?
Anyway, it's the same thing. You throw
it like this and it spins.
It has a blades on the outside like a
helicopter, and it has blades on the
inside.
Uh
and it cuts the person both ways, okay?
And that's called the crown of knives.
Uh
sometimes it comes down on your head,
and
that's what happened to me and John
Brady.
Uh no, I'm just kidding. Uh
we got it to go back up quickly. Uh
it'll cut you your head from the inside,
and then it cuts you from the outside
also. So, it's uh
the name of the of this lojong
is the crown of knives. And the idea is
uh
is that your karma comes back to you
like a like a like a wheel of knives,
okay? So, whatever you do to other
people
comes back to you like a crown of
knives, like a crown of knives. There's
a many beautiful
stories in here. One cool one is uh
the guy who makes a sword
on his anvil, a blacksmith who makes a
sword,
fancy sword
for a special rich guy,
and then carries it,
finishes it, and he carries it to the
rich guy, and he trips
on the way, and he stabs himself through
the heart.
And uh
they say that's the lojo. Got it?
Like uh you you intend to hurt somebody,
and you get all ready to hurt somebody,
and maybe you hurt somebody, but then it
comes back,
and it hurts you. The other example is
in this book is uh
poison arrow.
When and this guy is going to battle,
and he coats the
arrows with poison, and then in the
middle of the battle, he's really going
fast, and he
he cuts himself, and he dies. He dies in
the middle of battle. And they say that
our life is like that. Every time we
want to hurt somebody, every time we get
ready to hurt somebody,
uh it backfires on us. And that's the
idea of the wheel of
of knives at the crown of knives. The
ancient story
where we found the Sanskrit uh
is the story of Maitri.
Uh in the Karma Vibhanga, which This is
a sutra by Lord Buddha,
uh
1,500 years before Atisha.
And uh it's a story about a young man
who
goes to sea. You know the story.
And his mother asked him not to go, and
he insists on going,
and then uh
finally,
he's on his way out to go to sea. His
mother's holding on to his leg, and he
bumps his mother's head.
And then he goes to sea. At sea, the
ship sinks. Everyone dies except for the
young boy.
And there's a long story, but the karma
of hurting your parent
uh is that
he's got the wheel of knives on his
head.
Later, the wheel of knives comes to his
But Maitreya,
just as the wheel is descending onto his
head, he
makes a prayer
that he should take the pain of the
knives,
and it should
cause his parents to never have any
pain.
See what I mean? He said, "And here, by
the way, I'll take the pain of all
living beings on on myself."
And he welcomes the the crown of knives.
Therefore, the crown cannot
cannot it it it stops in midair, and it
won't come down. And uh
So, the translator was Zaya
and
at the time he was
have Well, he was like 5 years into the
book, and he had a son,
and he named his son Maitreya
in honor of the the boy in the story.
Okay? So, and
back in Indonesia, around the time of
Atisha or a little bit earlier,
uh they were building a pyramid, a grand
pyramid called Borobudur.
And um
there's a
It's got like uh
I think it has 1,200 panels the size of
this wall.
And they are carved. Uh famous Buddhist
stories are carved into the panels.
And there's a carving
of the story of Maitreya.
Uh
but unfortunately, it's on the first
level of the pyramid.
And it's backwards.
Okay? Like you walk around the pyramid
circumambulate clockwise and the panels
run backwards.
Something like that, okay? And they only
make sense if you're walking around the
pyramid in a certain direction, okay?
So, anyway, we found a drawing of the
crown of knives there.
Uh, we And by the way, those those
particular carvings were covered up
about 100 years ago.
Uh,
the pyramid was collapsing.
And so they bulldozed earth They
They buried the first
level of the pyramid, which happens to
be the story of my dream.
But someone Some crazy Indian
photographer took pictures of it first.
So, we have the pictures and we we drew
the crown of knives and you can see it
in the book.
Uh,
but the idea is of this lojong.
Why he said lojong lojong semjong
semjong
is that this
practice
of lojong
uh,
has two levels, okay? The practice has
two levels. And we've been talking about
it in the lamrim. By the way, lamrim
So, you you take a new new student or
you take a new country
and you teach them lojong first. So,
Atisha's teacher
gave him
this lojong and said, "Teach that to
them first."
And when they calm down
a little bit, you can teach them lamrim.
Okay? Start with lojong.
Uh,
you know, teach them lojong for about a
year.
And that's what my teacher did when he
got to the crazy land
called America. And and he taught lojong
for about a year.
And then second level you teach lamrim
when people are ready.
In a new country or something, first you
do lojong cuz it's short and it's
complete.
And then you teach lamrim
which is long and complete.
Okay, and if the people are serious
you then you teach them the great five
the five great books. Okay, the five
great books of philosophy. So that's
kind of what I've been doing for the
last 30 40 years. Okay?
So
do lojong then
lamrim for the busy people who have
phones and stuff.
And
and then
the serious people we do
uh
the classics, the five great books which
is the Geshe course. Okay, and it takes
like 20 years 25 years and uh
So that's what we're doing in the
translation classes.
And if you want to go deeper but the
topic
of all three
is lojong semjong semjong. First one
means
uh
try to feel the intention
to treat other people
as well as you treat yourself. Try to
treat other people
with the same love
that you treat yourself. Okay, try to
reach a state where you take care of
other people
with the same
interest and the same passion
that you take care of yourself. Okay,
that's the first lojong or semjong means
try to treat other people
with the same kind of uh
interest that you take care of yourself.
Okay, and by the way, we all take care
of ourselves
better than we take care of other
people, and that's just human nature. If
you're on this planet
right now and you're not Vajrayogini in
disguise, which you may be, I don't
know,
cuz you're disguised.
Uh
But everyone else of us, me,
we take care of ourselves better
than we take care of other people, and
that's just human
nature, and it's why we're here.
Cuz this is kind of like
the back of the class.
This planet is the back of the class.
But aren't we not supposed to shut up,
you guys?
5 more minutes? Something?
I got to time this, right?
Tim?
Serious?
Wow. Okay.
Oh.
5 10 minutes more?
So, half an hour more?
Oh, how long is the class?
Huh?
Okay.
It's another world.
Okay, good.
Uh so, the first sem jong means
I'm going to turn on
I have a phone.
No, I got a phone somewhere. Hang on.
I don't trust mountain time.
People are in another world.
Okay, 7:15, am I right?
Okay, right.
Uh so, the first lojong, first 10 jong
means uh practice the state of mind
where you try to
take care of other people with the same
passion
that you take care of yourself. Try to
equal it out. And that is called
deceptive
lojong
or first level lojong.
And uh there's two practices
that help you reach that level of
lojong. Okay, there's two famous
practices.
And they've come from Shantideva. They
come from 1,300 years ago.
300 years before
Atisha. Okay? And Atisha was trained
in Shantideva. So, he he knew about it.
And uh Shantideva's uh approach
is two parts. It's called Dagshen
Nyonglen, right?
Uh
say Dagshen.
Dagshen.
Nyonglen.
Uh
Dag means me, Shen means other people.
And then Nyonglen, people call it
exchanging self and others. It's not
It's not uh correct. Okay? Uh it's a big
uh boo-boo.
So, it's actually two different
practices. Nyong
and len. Okay? Dagshen,
me me and other people, Nyong
len.
So, Nyong Dagshen First Nyong, then len.
Not Nyonglen. Okay? Got it? So, here's
what the Nyong is. There's basically
Nyong means uh equal.
Nyong means equal. For example, there's
a famous Nyong Nyong Nyi, which which is
emptiness.
E- equality of all people and things
is their emptiness. There's nothing
in the universe which is not coming from
your seeds. There's nothing
in the universe
which is not coming from your seeds.
Nyampa.
All things are equal. Okay? Why?
Everything you ever see and everyone you
ever meet
is coming from your seeds, you know.
And I I don't know this week, I was
having an operation on my hand,
operation number two.
Uh
and uh people from chasing me around
town. I need a meeting. I need a
meeting.
You know, I'm like, I'm sorry. They're
cutting up my hand, you know. I mean,
you could come in the room,
but I might not be, you know,
conscious and
And then I'm like,
Then I was uh
You know, I'm like, okay.
Uh
What What do you need? I'm having
trouble. I'm having trouble with my wife
or my husband, you know. I say I just
say,
Think about the pen.
They're like, no, but I need more. And
I'm like, I don't have anything else.
That's all That's all I got, you know.
You know, really.
And that should be enough, you know. If
someone you're in
You know, nyam One meaning of nyam is
everything in the universe is equal.
It's all coming from you, okay? People
around you, even your husband,
is coming from you, okay? If you don't
like something,
fix it
in you, cuz it's all coming from you.
Then you don't have to worry about
anybody else. And you don't have to tell
Geshe La about anybody else.
Cuz I don't care.
Cuz I know the problem and I know how to
fix it.
Just fix your seeds, you know. Don't
I I don't care about this other thing,
you know? I I don't have anything else
to say.
You know, I can stretch it out as long
as I can.
Anyway, all things are equal, nyamba,
okay? All all things are coming from
you. Even the person who's giving you
the most trouble in your life is coming
from you. And and people beg me and and
yell at me and
call me over and over and say, "I need
more." And I say,
"I don't have more, you know?" Uh huh.
Just fix it, you know? You It's coming
from you. You fix it, you know? I can't
fix it.
You have to fix it. And
there's nothing that's not coming from
you. So,
you have
total control over the situation. You
just
If if your wife or husband's an
stop being an
Okay?
By the way, if my wife was here, I
wouldn't say that. Uh
So, anyway, that's the truth. Anyway,
that's one kind of equality, but the the
one here
is that
everyone has an equal right to be happy.
That's nyam. When you say dog shin nyam
je, nyam means
every living creature in the universe
has an equal right
to be happy. And and I don't have more
right than you to be happy. And you
don't have more right to me than than me
to be happy. We all have equal right.
Everyone has an equal right
to be happy. Okay, that's nyam.
And then it you just have to keep
thinking about it, you know? And we used
it, by the way, in DCI
for training business managers.
Like all the people on your work team
that you're They're to get to work for
you.
They have an equal right
to success that as you do. Okay, you're
the boss, you want them to work well,
but they have the same right as you.
They have the same right. They also want
to be successful. So, Nyam means
everyone has an equal right to be happy.
No No person
in the world has more right to be happy
than another person. And it sounds uh
obvious, right?
But it's hard to
do it, right? It's hard to
act on it, okay? Then J
is very tricky, you know. They say
exchange self and others. It's not that
easy.
Okay, you're supposed to
sit
in Baron's place
and I'm supposed to switch with you.
You're supposed to be in my body. I go
into your body.
I get in your body. I look through your
eyes at me.
And then I try to imagine how Baron's
feeling about Geshe Michael, you know.
Which Geshe Michael usually doesn't
worry about.
And then suddenly Geshe Michael's like,
"Whoa.
So, that's what Geshe Michael looks
like."
Okay?
Got it? So, the J part means It doesn't
mean uh
"Oh, your
Your happiness is important as mine."
Let's exchange. It doesn't mean that. It
means I put myself in your body
and I look back at Geshe Michael
and see how's he acting. How's he
treating people, you know? So, I try to
imagine
how you feel
yourself treated by Geshe Michael. How
do you feel
How do you feel Geshe Michael's treating
you?
It's J. It's the J. So, Nyam means
you have an equal right to happiness.
J means
I put myself in your body and look at
Michael
and then I see how it feels
to have Geshe how Geshe Michael treats
you. So So I think about how Geshe
Michael's treating me
which is you. Got it?
And then that helps you with the first
sem jong.
That's the first sem jong. I don't know
if it was Tara or Vajrayogini. I suspect
it was Tara.
She said sem jong the other night. I
said sem jong.
Okay. So the first sem jong is those two
practices. Dok shin nyam
jay. Okay. Uh that's the first sem jong.
And by the time you finish the first sem
jong
you're supposed to have
an overwhelming desire
to help people out of trouble. Okay?
You're supposed to have an overwhelming
desire
to help people get out of trouble. Okay?
That's the first sem jong.
Now
I you got to read this someday.
Uh
a lot of lojong's were kept secret.
And that fascinates me. You know, this
is like
first grade Buddhism, you know?
Kindergarten Buddhism.
You know?
And some of these lojong's were kept
secret
uh
for 800 years.
You know, they were passed down
secretly.
Uh if you guys you YSI guys, if you know
Virupa
is uh one of the great mahasiddhas, one
of the 80 great
yoga practitioners of ancient India is
Virupa.
And uh
he often he's By the way, vi means uh
in this case it means defective.
And rupa means uh his personal
appearance.
Rupa.
And Virupa means the Mr. Ugly.
And he's like one of the most famous
yogis of all time, you know. So,
who are you Geshla to call him Mr. Ugly?
Hey.
Somebody else named him, not me.
It's Virupa. And he's called
deformed
because he had a third eye.
Okay. And he looked weird.
Okay? Got it?
People just met him and said, "You look
weird."
You know, he's like blink blink.
Okay.
And that's Virupa.
And he
there's a there's a tradition that I
found in my research
that says some of the Lojong started
with him. That's
300 years before
Atisha.
You know,
uh
then I'm like first of all, I didn't
believe it. And then I went and checked
all the books by Virupa.
And there is a Lojong. It's not called a
Lojong, but the main topic is
Semjong Semjong.
Which makes it a Lojong, you know. And
I'm like, "Wow.
That's unbelievable. So, why did they
keep it secret
for 300 years up to Atisha?
And the Lojong Dondunma which the
Mexican teachers taught
partly in Guadalajara.
Uh
that was kept secret another couple
hundred years.
500 years, you know. Why?
Why keep the
Lojong secret? By the way, it took 12
years
for Atisha to learn
a lojong
that you can recite in 47 seconds.
I tried.
Like that, I timed it, 47 seconds. He
spent 12 years
learning a 47-second
prayer.
You know, what what's there that you can
spend 12 years on, you know? And why you
keep it secret? Ah, that's the second
sem-john.
Yeah.
That's the second sem-john. Okay, the
second sem-john means uh
practice the perception of emptiness
because otherwise you can't help other
people.
Okay, practice the perception of
emptiness.
Sem-john sem-john
because that's the only way you can
carry out
bodhicitta.
That's the only way you can become a
Buddha to help other people is the
second sem-john.
And
that's where the peacock comes from,
okay? So, there's a
very, very fam- famous
the second lojong that Atisha was taught
is called the
uh
majaduk jong semaja.
Duk jong.
Uh
how the peacocks destroy poison.
And uh you know the story
that
supposedly peacocks can eat poison
plants.
I'm thinking poison ivy. Have you ever
had poison ivy?
It's wonderful.
Uh
you touch the plant on your skin. I
mean, we don't have it in Arizona, which
is I mean, in this part of Arizona cuz
nothing grows here anyway.
Um
but uh
I I've had it for 3 4 months. It's in
New Jersey, in Jersey.
And uh it's this red uh thing and the
they love to eat it. The peacocks love
to eat it, you know. And and they eat
the poison ivy.
And uh and it makes them beautiful. It
gives them this beautiful colors, you
know.
And it and there's this whole idea that
we're going to talk about all week
that uh peacocks
we should be like a peacock, which means
we should look for trouble.
Okay? We should look for trouble. If
you're going to be a professional
Buddhist
you should look for trouble, you know.
And every time you see
a a a bad situation or a problem
you should peacock it.
You know, like you should jump in.
And most people uh when they see a
problem
they kind of
Well, they have they don't make it
obvious, you know. They just say, "Oh,
that's interesting." And
you know. And they don't
uh
usually they're too busy.
There was an interesting uh study they
they took people who were applying to
seminary
applying to become a priest.
And they gave them an interview date and
time.
And then they faked a car accident
in front of the interview building.
And they most of them just ran across
ignored the person bleeding and
didn't want to be late for their
religious interview.
Uh
and that's what we do, you know.
Like we don't
you know, we see trouble we just avoid
it. We go the other way. And a peacock
uh a bodhisattva
is supposed to seek out
problems
and eat them.
And and they get
sustenance, vitamins.
Problems are vitamins for Bodhisattvas.
You know, somebody says, "Geshe
we're having a fundraising problem, you
know."
Then you know,
what I really want to do at that moment
is take a nap.
And they're like, "Geshe we need to
raise more money, you know." And then
they go, "All right, peacock time."
And I I try to jump in and help out. You
know what I mean? Like that. So that's
peacock.
But
I believe
you cannot do it
unless you understand emptiness.
Okay? I believe that it would be
dangerous
to run around
eating poison
if you don't understand emptiness. Okay?
If you keep jumping into people's
problems
and making them yours, you will die.
Like the crow. There's a famous story of
the crow. He He saw the peacock eating
poison. He says, "I want to have those
feathers, you know."
And then the crow eats the poison and
they die.
I think the reason they kept it secret
was that
uh and they did not encourage people to
jump into all the problems they see
is that they would have a breakdown.
Or they would have a They would just
like get overwhelmed and and they would
freak out, you know? They'd end up in
the crazy house, you know? If you
actually
uh jumped into every possible problem
you saw to help,
you would go crazy. And unless you
understood
emptiness, which means you understand
that the problem is coming from you.
Okay? Then you can peacock.
Got it?
Like then it's your problem. It's not
like you're trying to help out somebody
else, you know, who made the problem.
You know? Oh, Geshe la, hands come from
from people, but not problems. Problems
come from their own side.
And then if you're if you're still at
that level
of blaming other people for their
problems,
like I just did at the beginning of
class, um
if you're still at that level, you you
can't be a Buddha self. You'll get
overwhelmed, and then you will quit the
problem business.
You will give up.
And you'll never do problems. So, I
think
my extensive research
The printer was like, I can't print it
in one volume. I said, "How about two?"
She said,
"I'll try." Then she said, "Three."
Then she said, "Four."
Then I said, "Do I have to pay the same
price?" "No, four times."
120 bucks.
Okay.
Uh
you know,
that's why it was secret
for for like 800 years, you know, until
the students could catch up on the
emptiness side,
it would be a disaster to encourage them
to
jump into people's problems, cuz they
would get overwhelmed, okay? They would
believe that they were other people's
problems, and they're not. They're your
problems. If you perceive a problem,
it's coming from you.
Then then you have the then you have the
power to
to fix it. You see what I mean? It would
be unfair
to send out all these peacocks,
crows,
to uh eat up everybody's problems, cuz
you'll have a breakdown, unless you
understand where it's coming from. And
then you can handle it, and then you can
help people, okay? And that's why
the two ladies said
Sam Jon Sam Jon. The second Sam Jon is
practice the state of mind of emptiness.
Otherwise,
you're going to get in trouble. You're
going to get overwhelmed. You're going
to have a break that You're going to
have a Dharma breakdown.
By the way, people who have a Dharma
breakdown are hopeless.
They get really mean.
They're like, "Yeah, I tried to help
her, but everybody gets a lot of They're
all
You know,
I gave that up. Oh, that was the old
days when I was
trying to be a Buddhist. Forget that.
Again, got it?